A Finding Aid to the Jo Hanson Papers, circa 1969-2009, in the Archives of American Art AAA.hansjo
Archives of American Art
Jo Hanson papers
circa 1969-2009
AAA.hansjo
Archives of American Art
4.3 Linear feet
The papers of San Francisco environmental artist and activist Jo Hanson measure 4.3 linear feet and date from circa 1969 to 2009. The papers document her professional activities through biographical material, project and exhibition files, printed material, artwork, and photographs. Also found are files regarding her participation in the Women's Caucus for Art.
Dickinson, Eleanor, 1931-
Hanson, Jo
Hendrickson, Barbara
Scope and Contents note
The papers of San Francisco environmental artist and activist Jo Hanson measure 4.3 linear feet and date from circa 1969 to 2009. The papers document her professional activities through biographical material, project and exhibition files, printed material, artwork, and photographs. Also found are files regarding her participation in the Women's Caucus for Art.
Of note within the collection is an oral history interview of Hanson, conducted by Eleanor Dickinson and Barbara Hendrickson in 2006-2007, as well was biographical documentation compiled for the interview. Hanson's installations "Crab Orchard Cemetery" and "Public Disclosure: Secrets From the Street" are also particularly well documented within this collection.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 6 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1976-2008 (0.6 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Project and Exhibition Files, circa 1973-2009 (0.8 linear feet; Box 1-2)
Series 3: Women's Caucus for Art, 1977-2006 (0.4 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1971-2008 (0.4 linear feet; Box 2)
Series 5: Artwork, 1969-circa 1990s (0.4 linear feet; Box 3, 5)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1969-2007 (1.7 linear feet; Boxes 3-5)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires and appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 2011 by Eleanor Dickinson, Hanson's friend.
Biographical/Historical note
Jo Hanson (1918-2007) was an environmental artist and activist in San Francisco, California. She was known for turning urban trash into works of art. She exhibited her work at the Corcoran Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C., Fresno Art Museum, and the Oakland Museum of California, among other places. In 1974 her installation "Crab Orchard Cemetery" toured nationally and included a mix of sculpture, printmaking, photography, and sound. During the 1980s she served on the San Francisco Arts Commission and championed the work of underrepresented women and artists of color. In 1996 she helped establish WEAD, the Women Environmental Artists Directory.
Women's Caucus for Art.; Art--Political aspects; Environmental artists; Interviews; Photographs; Sound recordings; Transcripts; Video recordings; Women artists--California--San Francisco
- Biographical Material, circa 1976-2008; Series 1; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Found here is biographical documentation on Jo Hanson. Included are a few documents created by Hanson, including artist statements, a resume, lists, and a biographical file compiled for a possible college course. Also found are one sound cassette recording of Hanson's memorial and a video cassette interview conducted in October, 2006. The bulk of this series consists of files regarding Hanson's oral history interview which was conducted by Eleanor Dickinson and Barbara Hendrickson from December 5, 2006 to February 7, 2007. Files include draft transcripts, sound cassette recordings, project correspondence, and extensive biographical documentation used in conducting the interviews. Also found is a sound recording and transcript of Eleanor Dickinson being interviewed by Barbara Hendrickson about her friendship with Hanson.
  - Resume, circa 1993 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Statements Regarding Trash Work, circa 1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Lists by Jo Hanson, circa 2000s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1981; undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Women, Appearance, and My History, circa 1976-1981 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jo Hanson Memorial, 2007 September 16; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Interview of Jo Hanson, 2006 October 10; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Oral History Interview Conducted by Eleanor Dickinson and Barbara Hendrickson, 2006-2007; 7 Sound cassettes (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - Oral History Transcript, Final, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Oral History Transcript, Drafts, 2006-2007 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Oral History Project Documentation, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Biographical Documents for Oral History, 2007-2008 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Eleanor Dickinson Files Regarding Jo Hanson, 1979-2007 (Box 1, Folder 15-20)
  - Eleanor Dickinson Reminiscing, 2007 June 13; 1 Sound cassettes Includes transcript. (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Project and Exhibition Files, circa 1973-2009; Series 2; 0.8 Linear feet Box 1-2
  Jo Hanson's project and exhibition files include correspondence, plans, photographs, printed material, and news clippings. Of note is extensive documentation on Hanson's installation work "Crab Orchard Cemetery" which toured nationally in the late 1970s, and her exhibition "Public Disclosure: Secrets From the Street" held at City Hall and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art in 1980.
  - "Totally Game Committee" Exhibition, circa 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 22-24)
  - Corcoran Rubbings Installation, circa 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Crab Orchard and Context" Notebook, circa 1979 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "Crab Orchard Cemetery" Exhibitions, circa 1975-180 (Box 1, Folder 27-31)
  - "Art That's Sweeping the City," Millbrae Art and Wine Festival, circa 1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - "Public Disclosure: Secrets From the Street" Exhibition, circa 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
  - "The Snail" Project, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - "Illegal Sights/Sites" Tour, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - "Recycled Artifacts" Exhibition, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - "Off-Site: Artists in Response to the Environment" Exhibition, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - "Open Studio" Exhibition, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Fresno Art Museum Exhibition and Gift, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - "Beaux & Eros" Exhibition, 2006-2007 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - "Crab Orchard Cemetery Revisited" Exhibition, 2007-2009 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Women's Movement Research Project, 1970s-2000s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Unidentified Project Documents, circa 1980s (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Women's Caucus for Art, 1977-2006; Series 3; 0.4 Linear feet Box 2
  Found here are Jo Hanson's files documenting her participation in the Women's Caucus for Art. Files may include caucus publications, event materials, meeting minutes, correspondence, photographs and other records. Of note are draft writings, correspondence, publications, and photographs documenting "A Day to Honor Women in the Arts" at the 1979 San Francisco Art Festival.
  - Regional Art History - Women, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - WCA Binder, 1978-circa 2002 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - San Francisco Art Festival, "A Day to Honor Women in the Arts", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 16-20)
  - International Dinner Party Honoring Marcelle Lebaudt, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - General Records, 2006; 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Honors, Hospitality in San Francisco, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Sun Gallery Exhibition, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - South Bay Chapter Conference on Aging, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Regional Conference, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Honor Awards Programs, 1988-2006 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Newsletters, 1996-2006; 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Printed Material, 1971-2008; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 2-3
  Printed material consists of publications regarding various events, a few exhibition catalogs, and newsletters. The bulk of the material found here are news clippings documenting Jo Hanson's art and community activities.
  - Event Announcements and Flyers, circa 1976-2006 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Event Buttons, circa 1982-1990 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Catalogs, 1982-2006 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - News Clippings, 1973-1995 (Box 2, Folder 33-36)
  - Newsletters, 1971-2008 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases, 1980-1992; 2006 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Publications Regarding Memorial Design, circa 1970s (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Women Environmental Artists Directory, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Artwork, 1969-circa 1990s; Series 5; 0.4 Linear feet Box 3, 5
  Found here are drawings, one sketchbook, and numerous original designs and graphics by Jo Hanson intended for note cards, business cards, flyers, and other projects. Also of note are Kodaliths printed by Hanson, a handmade book titled "The Artist's Pallet," and a drawing of Hanson by friend Eleanor Dickinson.
  - Oil Pastel Drawing, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ink Drawings, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Doodles, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sketchbook, "Old Work", undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Kerner Kodaliths and Negatives, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Wheelis Kodaliths, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Portrait of Jo Hanson by Eleanor Dickinson, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Flower Prints, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Business Card Artwork, circa 1990s (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Notecard Designs, 1972; 1993 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Parsley Leaf Stationery Design, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Xeroxes of Small Collages, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Hanson Collage, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Vortex Press Graphics, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "Messages From the Street" Title Page Design, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "The Artist's Pallet" Booklet, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Original Graphics for Cards, Flyers, Announcements, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
    Oversized items housed in Box 5
  - Oversized Original Graphics from Box 3, Folders 21-22, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 5)
- Photographs, circa 1969-2007; Series 6; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 3-5
  Found here are photographs and negatives primarily documenting Hanson's artwork and related projects including "Crab Orchard Cemetery." Photographs depict cemetery gravestones, foliage, and landscapes. Also found are a few installation photographs of her artwork and one album of artwork. The few personal photographs depict Jo Hanson and Eleanor Dickinson casting a sculpture in a studio, snapshots of Hanson at various events, and Hanson's funeral.
  - Photographs of Jo Hanson, circa 2006; Includes 1 CD-R of digital photographs (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Photographs of Jo Hanson and Eleanor Dickinson Casting, circa 1969 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Photographs of Jo Hanson Funeral, 2007; Includes 1 CD-R of digital photographs (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Personal Photographs, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 26-27)
  - Photographs of Neighborhood Clean-up, circa 1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Photograph of DPW Gothic, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Photographs of Deanza Installation, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Photographs of London, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Photographs of Foliage for Sawyer Show, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Photographs of Muybridge on Film and Stereoscopic Images, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Photographs of "Block-Heads", circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Photographs of Hendy Woods, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 35-42)
  - Photographs of Mono Lake, 1992 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Photographs of Unidentified Outdoor Location, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of "Burial Western-Style", 1970s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Cemetery Photographs, Negatives, and Slides, 1972-1973 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
  - Unidentified Photographs Taken by Jo Hanson, circa 1970s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of Artwork, circa 1960s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 9-17)
    Oversized item housed in Box 5
  - Photographs of Sculpture and Collage, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Photograph Album of Artwork, 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Photographs of Artwork by Hannah Chauvet, circa 2000s (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Negatives for Various Projects, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 21-28)
  - Miscellaneous Negatives, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Oversized Photograph of Artwork from Box 4, Folder 17, undated (Box 5)